Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Web Collection on Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp and War Crimes TAM.845
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Web Collection on Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp and War Crimes
September 2007-ongoing
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Act Against Torture
American Civil Liberties Union
Crimes of War Project
Center for Constitutional Rights (New York, N.Y.)
United States. Department of Justice. Office of Information Policy
Witness against Torture
WikiLeaks (Organization)
United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation
United States. Department of Justice. Office of the Inspector General
United States. Department of Defense
United States. Congress. Senate. Committee on Armed Services
Reprieve.
National Security Archive (U.S.)
TAM.845
62 websites in 62 archived websites.
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Web Collection on Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp and War Crimes (2007-ongoing) contains archived websites of legal and grassroots organizations critical of American policy relating to Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp and United States government treatment and torture of the detainees. It also includes government documents relating to detainee operations, abuses, and interrogations at Guantánamo Bay, Afghanistan, and Iraq.
Historical Note
The Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp was opened in 2002 in response to the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001 to detain suspected terrorists and "enemy combatants" by the Bush administration. Due to the nature of Guantánamo not being on American territory, detainees were held by the American government without charges or trial and subject to human rights violations and abuse. Legal organizations, protestors, politicians, and international bodies have called for the closure of Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp and worked to release detainees. As of this writing (January 2025), Guantánamo is still open and 15 detainees remain.
Scope and Contents
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Web Collection on Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp and War Crimes (2007-ongoing) contains archived websites of organizations critical of American policy relating to Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp and United States government treatment and torture of the detainees. In addition to grassroots organizations' protest work, legal organizations and non-profits' casework and activism on closing Guantánamo Bay and to secure civil and human rights for detainees are also documented in the collection.
The collection also includes many documents released using the Freedom of Information Act, relating to detainee operations, abuses, and interrogations at Guantánamo Bay, Afghanistan, and Iraq. These documents were published on government websites, the American Civil Liberties Union's websites, and the National Security Archive's websites.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Accruals
https://www.aclu.org/issues/national-security/detention/guantanamo-bay-detention-camp/, https://www.aclu.org/news/national-security/close-guantanamo/, https://reprieve.org/uk/, https://reprieve.org/us/, https://nsarchive.gwu.edu/project/torture-archive/, and https://www.aclu.org/issues/national-security/ are accrued semiannually.
https://ccrjustice.org/home/what-we-do/active-cases is accrued monthly.
Arrangement
The archived websites are arranged alphabetically by creator.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Custodial History
Tamiment Library, New York University began web archiving in 2007 as part of a grant given by the National Digital Information Infrastructure and Preservation Program (NDIIPP) of the Library of Congress. Websites were initially selected by Tamiment Library curators and captured through the use of the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2007 as part of the Guantanamo Bay Detention Camp & War Crimes (U.S.) Web Archive. In November 2015, these websites were migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. The accession number associated with the initial set of archived websites is 2009.050. For archived websites captured after 2018, the accession numbers associated with these websites are 2019.090, 2019.129, 2022.038, 2024.001, and 2025.014.
Related Materials
Guantanámo Bay Detention Camp Collection: Seton Hall University Law School Center for Policy and Research Records (TAM 472) Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp Collection: Dorsey and Whitney, LLP Records (TAM 509)
Torture -- United States; Iraq War, 2003-2011 -- Prisoners and prisons, American.; Iraq War, 2003-2011 -- Moral and ethical aspects -- United States.; War criminals -- United States.; Prisoners of war -- Abuse of; War crimes.; Lawyers -- Political activity -- United States.; Iraq War, 2003-2011 -- Protest movements -- United States.; Afghan War, 2001 -- Protest movements -- United States; Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp; Abu Ghraib Prison; United States. Freedom of Information Act
- Act Against Torture, July 2009-June 2017
  Historical Note
  Act Against Torture was a coalition of activists based in the Bay Area in California that worked to abolish torture and detention, to end United States intervention in Iraq and Afghanistan, and to prevent future wars. The organization opposed "Keep Gitmo Open" campaigns; called for the prosecution and firing of John Yoo; advocated for freeing the San Francisco 8; and called for shutting down the Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp.
  Scope and Contents
  The website contains photographs of protests and other actions, press coverage of the organization, news and background information related to human rights, fliers, factsheets, and other organizing materials. The website was active from 2005-2009.
  Content Warning
  This website contains graphic images of torture.
- American Civil Liberties Union, July 2009-ongoing
  Custodial History
  In 2010, http://www.aclu.org/safefree/index.html redirected to http://www.aclu.org/keep-america-safe-free. In 2012, http://www.aclu.org/keep-america-safe-free redirected to https://www.aclu.org/keep-america-safe-and-free-0. In 2015, http://www.aclu.org/accountability redirected to https://www.aclu.org/feature/accountability-torture/.
  In 2015, https://www.aclu.org/keep-america-safe-and-free-0 redirected to https://www.aclu.org/issues/national-security/. In 2016, https://www.aclu.org/feature/accountability-torture/ redirected under the host for https://www.aclu.org/issues/national-security/. https://www.aclu.org/issues/national-security/ was added to the web archives in 2018.
  - Accountability for Torture, July 2009-October 2016
    The website contains FOIA documents filed by the American Civil Liberties Union, their investigation of the torture program, analysis of United States Senate Report on CIA Detention Interrogation Program, press releases and news related to court cases and document requests, documents and news related to Mohamed et al. v Jeppesen Dataplan, Inc and Ali v. Rumsfeld et al, and an outline on how the Obama administration could redress the torture program. The website underwent a redesign and redirect in 2015.
    The Accountability for Torture Project of the American Civil Liberties Union, worked to hold the George W. Bush administration accountable for the treatment of prisoners in United States custody overseas. They worked to do this through FOIA requests, litigation, and action campaigns.
  - Close Gitmo and End Military Commissions, July 2009-December 2012
    Close Gitmo and End Military Commissions is a website of the American Civil Liberties Union Accountability for Torture Project.
    Contains news related to Guantánamo Bay, executive orders from President Obama related to the closing of Guantánamo Bay, and an FAQ related to detainees. The website was active from 2009-2011 and redirected to the ACLU page in 2012 on the 10th anniversary of the opening of Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp.
  - Close Guantánamo, February 2012-ongoing
    The Close Guantánamo website contains press releases and statements by the ACLU on the continued use of the Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp, an activist toolkit, infographics on the cost and detainees, and an outline on how the federal government can close Guantánamo. The webpage redesigned and redirected to a new URL in 2015 and 2022.
  - Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp, May 2015-ongoing
    Website containing news, commentary, press releases, campaign information, podcasts, and litigation related to ACLU's ongoing work with closing the Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp.
  - Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp Search Results, November 2023-November 2024
  - National Security Project, July 2009-ongoing
    Originally created as an informal working group after the September 2001 attacks, the National Security Project (NSP) advocated for national security policies that are consistent with the Constitution, the rule of law, and fundamental human rights. The Project litigated cases relating to detention, torture, discrimination, surveillance, censorship, and secrecy. Safe and Free at Home (later Keep America Safe and Free) is a campaign of the ACLU's National Security project.
    The National Security Project website contains news, FOIA requests, press releases, summaries of court cases and legal documents, legislative documents, blog posts, infographics, podcasts, and reports. Issues focused on in the project include torture, surveillance, secrecy, detention, discriminatory profiling, targeted killing, military commissions, dissent, and exclusion. The campaign Safe and Free at Home/Keep America Safe and Free was absorbed by the project in circa 2015.
- Center for Constitutional Rights, May 2008-ongoing
  List and accompanying documentation related to active cases of the Center for Constitutional Rights (CCR). Issues focused on by CCR include abusive immigration practices, corporate human rights abuses, criminalizing dissent, discriminatory policing, drone killings, government surveillance, the Guantánamo Bay detention camp, LGBTQIA+ persecution, mass incarceration, Muslim profiling, Palestinian solidarity, racial injustice, sexual and gender-based violence, torture, war crimes, and militarism.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  https://ccrjustice.org/home/what-we-do/active-cases website was added as a replacement for http://ccrjustice.org/cases-issue, which became defunct in 2014 and redirected to https://ccrjustice.org/home/what-we-do/active-cases in 2015. The website was added to the Guantanamo Bay Detention Camp & War Crimes (U.S.) Web Archive in 2018. The accession number associated with this website is 2019.090.
- Crimes of War Project, March 2009-October 2016
  Established in 1999, the Crimes of War Project is a collaboration of journalists, lawyers, and scholars that worked to raise awareness of the laws of war and their application to situations of conflict. Their goal was to promote understanding of international humanitarian law among journalists, policymakers, and the general public, in the belief that the knowledge of the legal framework governing armed conflict will lead to public pressure to prevent breaches of the law and to punish perpetrators. The website is based on the book Crimes of War: What the Public Should Know.
  The Crimes of War Project contains a glossary, commentary arranged by region, and other articles. It also includes the Killid Group Project on Journalism Training in Afghanistan and high school education projects. The website features analysis on the Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp, international law, and conflicts in Chechnya, Democratic Republic of the Congo, Liberia, Rwanda, Sierra Leone, Sudan, Uganda, Afghanistan, Cambodia, East Timor, Chile, Colombia, the Balkans, Iraq, and Israel/Palestine. The website was active from 1999-2011.
- National Security Archive, September 2009-ongoing
  The Torture Archive, published in 2009, centralizes primary source documents related to the "United States government policy on the detention and interrogation of individuals in the 'global war on terror' since September 11, 2001." The Archive includes records from ACLU lawsuits against the United States Department of Defense and other federal agencies; documents from the Combatant Status Review Tribunals (CSRT) and Administrative Review Boards (ARB); FOIA requests; and court documents from Writs of Habeas Corpus Petitions filed by Guantánamo Bay detainees.
  The website contains companion resources for the documentary Torturing Democracy, select documents in the National Security Archive, press releases on new documents added the Archive, and blog posts about the Archive. The database of documents is not captured in the web archives.
- Reprieve, March 2009-ongoing
  Reprieve is a legal action non-profit that investigates, litigates, and campaigns against human rights abuses. Issues focused on include ending the death penalty, closing the Guantánamo Bay Prison, stopping illegal and lethal drones, ending the use of torture, and unlawful detention. Reprieve and Reprieve US are two individual organizations but work closely together and share financial resources. Reprieve US focuses on litigation in the United States, whereas Reprieve focuses more globally.
  The website contains casework, policy and research, media and reports, newsletters, creative projects, action campaigns, petitions, and news. Investigation topics include the CIA drone program, detention at Guantánamo Bay, ending executions and lethal injections, the death penalty, the Pakistan Police Torture project, secret prisons, and the United Kingdom's government complicity in torture. Materials on the website date back to 2005.
- United States Department of Defense, June 2009-March 2016
  - Combatant Status Review Tribunal (CSRT) and Administrative Review Board (ARB) Documents, June 2009-March 2016
    Contains unclassified summaries of evidence for Combatant Status Review Tribunals held between July 2004 and July 2007. Included are summaries for High Value Detainees (HVD).
  - Combatant Status Review Tribunals/Administrative Review Boards, July 2009-August 2010
    The webpage contains administrative review board procedures notifications and summaries, photos, news releases, news articles, instructions, and briefing transcripts. Also includes a biography of Captain Frank Sweigart, and unclassified summaries, transcripts, and audio of hearings for Abu Faraj al-Libi, Walid Bin Attash, Khalid Shaykh Muhammad, Ramzi Bin al-Shib, Ahmed Khalfan Ghailani, Mohd Farik bin Amin "Zubair", Mustafa Al Hawsawi, Al Nashiri, Abd Al Rahim Hussein Mohammed, Bashir Bin Lap (also known as Lillie), Ammar Al Baluchi, Rjduan Bin Isomuddiiu (also known as Hambali), Zayn Al Abidin Muhammad Husayn (also known as Zubaydah), Guleed Hassan Ahmed, and Majid Khan.
  - Detainee Death Investigation, November 2009-March 2016
    Contains documents released in litigation concerning three detainee deaths at the Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp on June 10, 2006.
  - Detainee Related Documents, June 2009-February 2016
    Contains documents related to Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp detainees obtained/posted via the Freedom of Information Act on the website of the Office of the Secretary of Defense and Joint Staff Reading Room. Documents are dated from 2005-2009.
  - Detainees Investigations Briefing Transcripts, July 2009
    Briefing transcripts, interviews, and speeches related to Abu Ghraib, Donald Rumsfeld, and Guantánamo Bay.
  - Detainees Investigations Special Reports, July 2009-March 2016
    Contains reports related to detainee operations and abuses at Guantánamo Bay and Abu Ghraib, independent panel reports, and Army Inspector General reports. Reports date from 2004-2005.
- United States Department of Justice, Office of Information Policy, November 2009-November 2021
  Posts on the FOIA Post blog. Contains summaries of Federal court decisions pertaining to the Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp that were received by the Office of Information Policy.
  - Summaries of New Decisions -- August 2007, November 2009-November 2021
  - Summaries of New Decisions -- June 2008, November 2009-November 2021
  - Summaries of New Decisions -- October 2008, November 2009-November 2021
  - Summaries of New Decisions -- January 2009, November 2009-November 2021
  - Summaries of New Decisions -- September 2009, November 2009-November 2021
- United States Department of Justice, Office of the Inspector General, November 2009-November 2024
  - Semiannual Report to Congress, November 2009-November 2024
    Contains an Office of the Inspector General report to Congress regarding the Federal Bureau of Investigations involvement in and observation of detainee interrogations in Guantánamo Bay, Afghanistan, and Iraq. Report covers the period of April 1, 2008-September 30, 2008.
  - Statement of Glenn A. Fine (Inspector General, U.S. Department of Justice) before the House Committee on Foreign Affairs Subcommittee on International Organizations, Human Rights, and Oversight concerning "The Role of the FBI at Guantánamo Bay", November 2009-October 2020
    Contains testimony of the Office of the Inspector General given on June 4, 2008 regarding the Federal Bureau of Investigation's observation of and involvement in detainee interrogations at the Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp.
  - Statement of Glenn A. Fine (Inspector General, U.S. Department of Justice) before the Senate Committee on the Judiciary concerning "Detainee Interrogation Techniques", November 2009-October 2020
    Contains testimony of the Office of the Inspector General given before the Senate Committee on the Judiciary on June 10, 2008 regarding the Federal Bureau of Investigation's observation of and involvement in detainee interrogations at the Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp.
- United States Federal Bureau of Investigation, August 2009-November 2024
  - Detainees Positive Responses, August 2009-November 2024
    The FBI on January 2, 2007 released documents related to an internal inquiry in 2004 of FBI personnel who had served at Guantánamo Bay, Cuba since September 11, 2001 and had observed any aggressive interview techniques, interrogations, or mistreatment of detainees by representatives of law enforcement, the military, or the FBI. There were no documented incidents involving FBI personnel.
  - Guantánamo Bay Inquiry, November 2009-June 2017
    Contains a survey of 493 Federal Bureau of Investigation personnel asking whether they observed aggressive mistreatment, interrogations, or interview techniques at the Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp.
- United States Senate Committee on Armed Services, July 2009-March 2016
- Wikileaks, November 2007-November 2021
  Contains the United States Department of Defense Joint Task Force Guantánamo (JTF-GTMO) standard operating procedures (SOP) for Camp Delta (Guantánamo Bay prison), 2003 and related documents. This is the primary document for the operation of Guantánamo Bay, including the securing and treatment of detainees. The document is extensive and includes, in addition to text, various forms, identity cards and even Muslim burial instructions.
  Wikileaks, founded by Julian Assange in 2006, is a multinational organization that publishes "large datasets of censored or otherwise restricted official materials involving war, spying and corruption."
- Witness Against Torture, September 2007-ongoing
  Witness Against Torture, formed in 2005, was established when 25 Americans went to Guantánamo Bay and attempted to visit the detention facility. The group organized nonviolent direct actions, such as hunger strikes, demonstration, and other acts of civil disobedience. Annually, on January 11, they hold events and vigils to mark the anniversary of the first prisoners brought to Guantánamo Bay in 2002. In 2008, the 100 Days Campaign was a campaign organized by Witness Against Torture to close the Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp and end torture and rendition by the United States within the first 100 days of the Obama administration, mostly focusing on Uighur detainees and the expansion of the Bagram Theatre Internment Facility. The group held daily vigils outside of the White House and met with United States representatives.
  The January 11 Day of Action Against Guantánamo was an action organized by Witness Against Torture, marking the 10th anniversary of the opening of Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp in 2012. During the two-week hunger strike associated with the action, five activists were also on trial for unlawful conduct related to speaking out against an "appropriations bill containing a measure to strip funding from any efforts to repatriate Guantánamo detainees" in the House of Representatives.
  The websites contain information on the annual January 11 actions, their campaign calling the Obama administration to close Guantánamo during the first 100 days of his presidency, photos from the actions and at visits to Cuba, biographies of detainees, detainee letters, activist testimonies, book and film resources, and news and press releases related to Guantánamo Bay and Bagram Detention facilities.